William B. Young Collection of the Connecticut Company 2012.0077
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
BERA has 14 cars from six divisions of the Connecticut Company: New Haven (500, 614, 775, 865, 401(923), 1414, 1425, 1602), Hartford (1802), Waterbury (1330, 1911), Middletown (2350), Norwalk (1199) and Torrington (3000). In addition, a number of Connecticut Company cars are preserved at the Connecticut Trolley Museum and the Seashore Trolley Museum.
BIBLIOGRAPHY
Transportation Bulletin (Connecticut Valley Chapter NRHS); Electric Railway Journal; Connecticut Company records; Connecticut Company roster; Weller, John L., “The New Haven Railroad, Its Rise and Fall”; “Report of the Joint Commission on the New York, New Haven & Hartford R.R. Co.”, 1911; Connecticut Public Utilities Commission reports
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Connecticut Company.; Blueprints.; Correspondence.; Maps.; New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad.; Notes.; Photocopies.; Photographic negatives.; Photographic prints.; Postcards.; Reports.; Street-railroads.; Timetables.
- Series I: Car roster database and finding guides compiled by William B. Young, 1992, 2012
  - Printouts of database, 1992, 2012 (Box 1)
    Scope and Content Note
    Printouts include versions printed in 1992 and 2012, the latter after Mr. Young's death when the electronic version of the database was donated by his family to the Shore Line Trolley Museum in East Haven, Connecticut. The 2012 printout available here were provided by the trolley museum.
  - Finding guides to database, 2012 (Box 2)
    These guides were prepared by Mr. Young's family to accompany and provide reports for the database printouts. Included in the guides is a car summary organized by car number, owner, purchase cost, weight, roof, type, builder, year built, and its history of owners. The car history report is organized by owner, the dates the car was acquired, building, first in service, accident history, left the division, etc., motor type and numbers, compressor type, and controller. The rosters give snapshots of the cars owned by the company in 1900, 1908, 1916, 1930, 1940, and 1948.
- Series II: Research materials about the Connecticut Company system, undated, 1914-2005
  - Rosters, lists, notes, correspondence (from WBY to other enthusiasts), and car assignment track sheets, 1947, 1986, 1999-2005 (Box 3)
    Of particular interest:
    Lists specific to car builders including Jackson & Sharp, St. Louis Car Company, and Cincinnati Car Company.
  - Maps, correspondence, photocopies from reports and writings, 1916, 1923-1926, 1933, 1986-2000 (Box 6)
    Includes extensive notes for each trolley division, information about wrecks involving the cars, track layouts and building plans for entire system, notes about rosters and cars from writers and enthusiasts Thomas McNamara, Roger Borrup (editor of Trolley Days in Connecticut) and Fred Bennett, car assignment lists, and Mr. McNamara's writing about "Football and the Open Cars" (when the New Haven Division of the Connecticut Company provided trolleys to bring football fans to the Yale Bowl for Yale University football games).
  - Manuals, blueprints, notes, undated, 1914-1921, 2000 (Box 7)
    Includes the report "Standard Practice and Specifications for the Installation and Maintenance of Electrical Supply Lines, Signal Lines and Utilization Equipment by Office Chief Engineer Power & Equipment, New Haven, Conn. [of the Connecticut Company], valuation summaries of cars and equipment, listing of cars for the Branford Electric Railway, blueprints for the renumbering of cars, and a writing about "System Wide Car Numbering, Adopted 1915," by Fred Bennett.
  - Folders of compiled photocopied data about Connecticut Company cars in the following divisions: Bridgeport, Derby, Hartford, Meriden, Middletown, New Britain, New Haven, New London, Norwalk, Stamford, Torrington, and Waterbury, undated (Box 8)
  - Notes, correspondence, photocopies, reports and blueprints, 1921, 1924, 1958, 1986-1987, 2001-2002 (Box 12)
    Report on the Transportation Property of the Danbury and Bethel Street Railway Company as of March 1, 1924; Lists of buses that were in the Connecticut Company fleet; Central New England Railway electrification; division mileage; snow plowing; list of unserviceable cars of the Bridgeport Division; lists of roll signs; valuations and copies of inventories of equipment for divisions; correspondence from O.R. Cummings and Ed Wadhams; copies from railroad commissioners reports; blueprint of New Milford lease plans and track use; New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad stock book (undated), listing cars by type.
  - Maps, blueprints, reports, manuscripts, undated, 1915, 1923, 1939, 1960, 2005 (Box 13)
    Notes and drafts for a writing about street railways of the Connecticut Company system; Register of Arrival and Departure of Trains (1923); New Haven Railroad signal codes and electrification information; maps and plans of Lake Quassapaug along the Woodbury & Waterbury Railway; valuation map of New Haven, Connecticut (V.52.61/ST1A); detailed plans of routes of the street railway system throughout Connecticut; blueprint of a plan of the Roxbury, Connecticut, station (1939); Report of the Renumbering of Cars, All Divisions from the Connecticut Company Chief Engineer of Power & Equipment (August 1, 1915); inventories of trolley cars to be scrapped in various divisions and cars towed for junking; notes and correspondence with other rail enthusiasts about trolley cars.
  - Blueprints of a New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad standard 78 lb. rail and splice (1915, revised 1916); Roster of cars for all divisions (undated), undated, 1915 (Box 18)
  - Public Utilities Commission appraisals (bound volumes), 1919, 1928
    - Waterbury, Middletown, Torrington, New London, Stamford, Norwalk and Bridgeport, 1919 (Box 9)
    - Hartford, Meriden, New Britain, New Haven and Derby, 1919 (Box 10)
    - Special track work locations and details of make-ups, all divisions; Bridges and culverts, electric switch and signal locations, bonding - special work locations and details; Prices as of the 1910-1914 level, summaries, price units, 1919 (Box 11)
    - Public Utilities Commission valuations, 1928 (Box 19)
- Series III: Public timetables, 1877-1947
  - Connecticut Company, 1904-1947 (Box 15)
    Timetables span all Connecticut Company divisions, including Bridgeport, Hartford, New Britain, New Haven, Norwich, and Waterbury. Includes timetables for routes between the following towns: New London - Norwich - Willimantic, New Haven - Waterbury, New Haven - Milford and Milldale, Bridgeport - Norwalk, Hartford - New Britain, and others.
  - New Haven Railroad and predecessor companies, 1877-1911 (Box 14)
    All the timetables are arranged chronologically. Predecessor rail lines include the Old Colony Railroad, the New York, Providence & Boston Railroad, and the Housatonic Railroad. Lines west and east timetables of the New Haven Railroad are integrated within each other, organized in the general chronological order.
- Series IV: Travel guides, 1872-1947
  Almost all of the guides in this series are of excursions in New England, with a very few in New York State.
  - Trolley excursions, 1886-1936 (Box 16)
  - Railroad excursions, 1872-1947 (Box 17)
    Predominantly of locations along the New Haven Railroad.
- Series V: Postcards (Connecticut towns), undated
  Series contains 413 postcards with the emphasis on trolleys in Connecticut towns. The postcards themselves are generally undated but several are postmarked with dates from the early 1900s.
  - A-N, undated (Box 4)
  - N-Z, undated (Box 5)
- Series VI: Photographic prints, photographic negatives, glass negatives, printouts of images and images on pages from books, undated (ca. 1905-1940s) (Box 20)
  Images are almost exclusively of street railway cars of the Connecticut Company, all divisions. Of particular interest is a "Giant Coaster" at Lakewood Park in Waterbury, Connecticut (1930-1935); and two glass negatives of plans of the Waterbury to Woodbury division showing traffic concentrations points and distribution of population, both in 1918.